Guide to the John Farquhar Fulton Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Farquhar Fulton papers
1892-1988
1920-1960
MS 1236
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
137.25
(321 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, memoranda, writings, photographs, and memorabilia, which document the career of John Farquhar Fulton as a neurophysiologist, medical historian, and bibliophile. The files also include personal and professional letters which reflect his involvement in organizations and projects including his work with the National Research Council, particularly in aviation medicine and in editing a medical history of World War II. Fulton's writings concern physiological and medical discoveries and those who made them. His close association with Harvey Cushing resulted in voluminous files on major writing and editing projects. Correspondence with family and colleagues reflects his travels, hospitality, and his collecting interests. Fulton's teaching and research are only sparsely represented in the papers.
Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Historical Library, 1980-1995; gift of Mrs. Ruth Judge, 1992 and 1994; and gift of Jay B. Dean, 2006.
Related Material
John Farquhar Fulton Papers, Cushing/Whitney Medical Historical Library, Yale University Library.
Scope and Contents
The John Farquhar Fulton Papers document John Fulton's career as a neurophysiologist, medical historian, bibliophile, and administrator. They include correspondence, writings, organizational files, personal papers, and photographs which reflect Fulton's interest in the history of early scientific and medical discoveries. The papers also highlight Fulton's passion for book collecting and his efforts to foster notable collections in the history of medicine, including the Army Medical Library. This work culminated in the founding of the Yale Medical Historical Library, and the papers trace Fulton's close association with his collaborators on this project, Harvey Cushing and Arnold Klebs. The papers also contain an extensive record of Fulton's involvement, during World War II, with the work of the National Research Council, particularly with the Committee on Aviation Medicine and Subcommittee on Decompression Sickness, and his chairmanship of a project to prepare a medical history of the war.
The papers illustrate the possible reasons for Fulton's success in various undertakings: the extensive circle of his acquaintances; his consultative approach; his ability to engage large numbers of people, spread over two continents, in projects; and his overall enthusiasm. Fulton's expertise in the arts of the book (typography, layout, book design) and his careful attention to meticulous bibliographic records are also easily discernible. The papers have only sparse information (scattered correspondence, syllabi, and fragmentary notes) on Fulton's teaching and research. The files contain neither laboratory notebooks nor other research data from his work in the Yale Laboratory of Physiology.
The papers are arranged in five series which, for the most part, reflect Fulton's own arrangement of his files. The bulk of the papers dates from the 1920s to the 1960s. Series I, the General Files, consists of individual and organizational correspondence, which comprise almost two-thirds of the papers. Series II, Special Subjects, documents organizations in which Fulton was active as well as historical and bibliographic projects on which he worked. This series also includes correspondence, in addition to memoranda, agendas, minutes of meetings, and notes. Series III, Writings, contains documentation on Fulton's long and productive career as a writer and lecturer. It includes drafts of published and unpublished works arranged with correspondence related to these efforts. Series IV, Personal and Family Papers, includes John Fulton's memorabilia and personal and financial papers, as well as the correspondence of Lucia Fulton and other members of the Fulton, Wheatland, and Wheaton families. Series V, Visual Images, contains portraits; photographs of family and colleagues, travels, and residences; and several reels of undated 16 mm. film depicting social events and the results of physiological experiments.
The arrangement and the content of each series are more fully analyzed in the series description at the beginning of the inventory of that series. Because documentation on some topics appears in more than one series, cross-references are included in the inventory to each series. These are extensive but not all-inclusive. In the series inventories, Fulton's writings are referred to by the number assigned in the last published bibliography of his writings which appeared in the Journal of the History of Medicine and Allied Sciences, volume xvii, number 1, 1962.
Though the Fulton Papers were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from the Yale Medical Historical Library in 1980, additional Fulton documentation, particularly that relating to the history of the Medical Historical Library, remains there. The bound volumes of Fulton's voluminous diary, collected correspondence, and additional writings and personal memorabilia are there, as are chapter drafts for Elizabeth Thomson's incomplete biography of Fulton. Fulton's diary is also available on microfilm. Where appropriate, this material has been cross-referenced with the indication "See:" or "See also: Cushing/Whitney Medical Historical Library."
Biographical / Historical
John Farquhar Fulton was born in St. Paul, Minnesota on November 1, 1899, son of John Farquhar Fulton, an ophthamologist, and Edith Stanley Wheaton Fulton. Fulton received his B.S. degree from Harvard University in 1921 and went as a Rhodes Scholar to Oxford University, receiving his B.A. degree from Magdalen College in 1923. He remained at Oxford as a Christopher Welch scholar during 1923-1925 and was granted M.A. and D. Phil. degrees in 1925. He was a demonstrator in physiology and worked closely with Sir Charles Sherrington during those two years. He then returned to Harvard to study for his medical degree.
After graduating in 1927, Fulton became an associate in neurological surgery at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital in Boston. He returned to Oxford from 1928 to 1930 as demonstrator in physiology and fellow of Magdalen College. He was appointed professor of physiology at Yale University in 1929 and, on his return to the United States the following year, was made Sterling professor of physiology. He also served as chairman of the Laboratory of Physiology. He relinquished these posts in 1952 to become the first Sterling professor of the history of medicine at Yale University. In 1960 he was named to head the new Department of History of Science and Medicine but did not live to assume the chair.
Fulton was considered an authority in comparative physiology of the primate brain, neurophysiology, aviation medicine, and medical history. He established the first primate physiology laboratory in the United States. He investigated the functional interrelations of various parts of the brain, the significance of overlapping somatic and autonomic motor functions and the effects of experimental lesions. With Carlyle Jacobsen, one of his students, he observed the effect of prefrontal lobotomy on a neurotic chimpanzee. This operation was later used on humans to alleviate certain mental disorders resistant to other types of treatment, but the most significant results of this work were the data revealed on the relationship between the brain and the intellect. Fulton was especially successful in relating neurophysiological backgrounds to modern clinical neurosurgery. He brought outstanding lecturers from around the world to enrich the educational experience of his students.
During the Second World War, Fulton served on the National Research Council as a member of the Committee on Aviation Medicine. He chaired the Sub-committee on Historical Records from 1940 to 1946, was vice-chairman of the Division of Medical Sciences in 1943, and chairman of the Sub-committee on Decompression Sickness from 1940 to 1946. He was also liaison to The British Medical Council. Fulton organized the Yale Aeromedical Research Unit to do research on physiological problems associated with aviation medicine. In addition, he created the Yale Faculty Committee for Receiving Oxford and Cambridge Children, Inc. to provide refuge for children in the United States during the bombing of Britain.
Almost from boyhood, Fulton was interested in collecting ancient books dealing with the development of science and medicine. He developed friendships with book dealers and other bibliophiles. His collection included approximately 11,000 titles dating from the sixteenth century to the twentieth century. Fulton brought together the collections of Harvey Cushing, Arnold Klebs, and his own to develop the Yale Medical Historical Library into one of the world centers devoted to the history of medicine and the sciences.
Fulton was considered an outstanding bibliophile. His interest in the history of early physiological and medical discoveries and in those who made them resulted in special collections and published bibliographies dealing with the works of Robert Boyle, Kenelm Digby, Michael Servetus and Girolamo Fracastoro.
Fulton wrote more than four hundred articles and nearly thirty books, including Physiology of the Nervous System, which was translated into Spanish, Russian, Portuguese, French, Japanese, and German, and the much praised Harvey Cushing, a Biography. He belonged to almost sixty societies, was honored by the governments of a dozen countries, and received nine honorary degrees, in addition to many awards and decorations.
Fulton was married in Oxford, England to Lucia Pickering, daughter of Richard Wheatland of Topsfield, Massachusetts on September 29, 1923. Soon after the couple returned from England, they established their residence at 100 Deepwood Drive in Hamden, Connecticut, where they entertained students, fellows, and visitors from around the world. John Fulton died on May 29, 1960.
Arrangement
The John Farquhar Fulton papers are arranged in five series: I. General Files, 1910-1960. II. Special Subjects, 1892-1965. III. Writings, 1914-1960. IV. Personal and Family Papers, 1884-1988. V. Visual Images, 1899-1965.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Journal of neurophysiology; Aviation medicine; Bibliomania; Book collecting; Booksellers and bookselling; Decompression sickness; Frontal lobotomy; Medicine -- History; Neurophysiology; Physiology; Rhodes scholarships; World War, 1939-1945 -- Children -- Great Britain; World War, 1939-1945 -- Evacuation of civilians -- Great Britain; Photographs; Medical historians; Aring, Charles D., 1904-; Bailey, Percival, 1892-1973; Baumgartner, Leona, 1902-1991; Berg, Margaret; Booraem, Laura Fulton; Boyle, Robert, 1627-1691; Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Bucy, Paul C.; Cairns, Hugh, Sir, 1896-1952; Clendening, Logan, 1884-1945; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; De Haven, Hugh; Denny-Brown, Derek, 1901-1981; Du Bois, Eugene F. (Eugene Floyd), 1882-1959; Dusser de Barenne, Joannes Gregorius, 1885-1940; Duveen, Denis I.; Eisenhardt, Louise, 1891-1967; Evans, Herbert; Fishbein, Morris, 1889-1976; Flexner, Louis B. (Louis Barkhouse), 1902-1996; Florey, Howard, Baron Florey, 1898-1968; Francis, William Willoughby, 1878-; Franklin, Kenneth J. (Kenneth James), 1897-1966; Fulton, Edith; Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960; Fulton, John Farquhar, 1856-1932; Fulton, Lucia Pickering, 1899-1989; Garrison, Fielding H. (Fielding Hudson), 1870-1935; Gerard, R. W. (Ralph Waldo), 1900-1974; Gibson, William C. (William Carleton), 1913-2009; Harvey, E. Newton (Edmund Newton), 1887-1959; Hoff, Ebbe Curtis, 1906-1985; Hoff, H. E. (Hebbel Edward), 1907-; Howell, William H. (William Henry), 1860-1945; Hubbell, Florence Fulton; Hubbell, Ralph; Ingraham, Franc D. (Franc Douglas), 1898-1965; Jacobsen, Carlyle Ferdinand, 1902-; Keller, Allen D.; Kennard, Margaret; Keynes, Geoffrey, 1887-1982; Kisch, Bruno, 1890-1966; Klebs, Arnold C. (Arnold Carl), 1870-1943; Lamport, Harold, 1908-1975; Larkey, Sanford V. (Sanford Vincent), 1898-; Leake, Chauncey Depew, 1896-1978; Liddell, Edward George Tandy, 1895-1981; Light, Richard Upjohn, 1902-1994; Livingston, Robert B. (Robert Burr), 1918-2002; Lorente de Nó, Rafael; Malloch, Archibald, 1887-; Mark, E. L. (Edward Laurens), 1847-1946; Meagher, Richard Dennis; Muirhead, Arnold; Nachmansohn, David, 1899-1983; O'Malley, Charles Donald; Penfield, Wilder, 1891-1976; Pijoan, Michel; Relf, Louise Fulton; Rosencrantz, Esther; Ruch, Theodore Cedric, 1906-; Schullian, Dorothy M. (Dorothy May), 1906-1989; Schuman, Henry; Servetus, Michael, 1511?-1553; Sheehan, Donal; Stevenson, Lloyd G., 1918-; Thomas, Charles C. (Charles Crankshaw), 1904-; Vesalius, Andreas, 1514-1564; Viets, Henry R. (Henry Rouse), 1890-1969; Walker, A. Earl (Arthur Earl), 1907-1995; Weed, Lewis H. (Lewis Hill), 1886-1952; Yerkes, Robert M. (Robert Mearns), 1876-1956; Zuckerman, Solly, Baron, 1904-1993; Wheatland family; American Medical Association; American Philosophical Society; Army Medical Library (U.S.); Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease; George Banta Company; Harvey Cushing Society; Medical Library Association; National Research Council (U.S.); Osler Library; W.B. Saunders Company; Yale Medical Library; Yale Medical Library. Historical Library; Yale University. Department of Physiology; Yale University. School of Medicine
- General Files, 1910-1960; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series reflects John Fulton's multi-faceted career and the wide travels, well-known hospitality, and energetic collecting typical of his professional and social milieu. Correspondence comprises the bulk of the files. Fulton's major correspondents include physiologists, physicians, bibliophiles interested in the history of medicine, book dealers, former students, learned institutions, editors and publishers, and family members. The files for institutions and associations indicate Fulton's broad range of professional involvement. They include the American Philosophical Society, History of Science Society, Rhodes Scholarship Trust, the American Medical Association, the Harvey Cushing Society, and the Institute for Advanced Study. In addition to correspondence, these files contain minutes, reports, agendas, notes, and other documents.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by personal, corporate or institutional name, or periodical title. The container listing for the series includes a large number of cross-references directing the researcher from a personal or corporate name to related material. When correspondence with colleagues refers to their committee work together, additional material will be found under the name of the committee.
  The series documents Fulton's preoccupation with history of medicine in the files of Leona Baumgartner, Logan Clendening, Dennis Duveen, Herbert Evans, William C. Gibson, Kenneth Franklin, Geoffrey Keynes, Sanford Larkey, Chauncey Leake, Arnold Muirhead, Charles Donald O'Malley, and Esther Rosencrantz. Fulton's devotion to libraries is demonstrated in the files for the Osler Library, the Gest Library, the Yale University Library, and the Yale Medical Library, and in his exchanges with librarians William W. Francis, Lloyd Stevenson, Henry Viets, and Dorothy Schullian and the Medical Library Association.
  Day-by-day developments in the construction of the Yale Medical Library and the creation of the Yale Medical Historical Library are chronicled in the Arnold Klebs correspondence. It shows the frequency and intensity of the medical as well as bibliophilic exchanges between the two close friends. These files contain the original letters that Klebs wrote to Fulton as well as of Fulton's original letters to Klebs. Fulton apparently combined his files with correspondence found in Klebs's papers, when Klebs sent his library to New Haven. There is little correspondence between Fulton and the other major donor to the Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing. Fulton's exchanges with his mentor Cushing are almost entirely in the Harvey Williams Cushing Papers (MS 160).
  Medical Historical Library staff members Madeline Stanton and Elizabeth Thomson collaborated with Fulton on many of his writing, editing, and book collecting projects. They also facilitated Fulton's assiduous record-keeping of his own experiences and coped with the voluminous files of his correspondence. Their files in this series, however, are routine. Additional material can be found in the Madeline Stanton Papers (MS 1482) and the Elizabeth Thomson Papers (MS 1623). Drafts for Elizabeth Thomson's unfinished biography of Fulton are in the Medical Historical Library.
  The series provides evidence of Fulton's dedication to science and medical research. Fulton's early scientific experiences are documented in the files for Edward L. Mark and the "Bermuda Biological Station." Files on colleagues from Fulton's time at Oxford include those for Hugh Cairns, Edward G. T. Liddell, Archibald Malloch, and Wilder Penfield; those at the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital include Percival Bailey, Franc Ingraham, Richard Meagher, and Michel Pijoan. In exchanges with Howard Florey, Margaret Kennard, Carlyle Jacobsen, and Robert B. Livingston, Fulton discusses penicillin and neurophysiology as well as personal matters. The correspondence with Robert Yerkes traces the sharing of Yale facilities by Fulton and Yerkes in their work with chimpanzees.
  The Yale Laboratory of Physiology was an important training ground for graduate, post graduate, and mid-career scientists. Former fellows of the Laboratory of Physiology continued to consult Fulton and to share research developments as they pursued their careers. There is correspondence in the series between Fulton and former research fellows Ebbe and Hebbel Hoff, Paul Bucy, Harold Lamport, Robert Burr Livingston, Donal Sheehan, Theodore Ruch, Hsiang-Tung Chiang, Derek Denny-Brown, Charles D. Aring, Allen D. Keller, Richard U. Light, William G. Mahoney, Arthur Earl Walker, and James W. Watts. The files of the Yale School of Medicine include the annual reports of the Department of Physiology/Physiological Sciences and the Laboratory of Physiology. Though voluminous, the bulk of these files concerns routine administrative matters.
  Fulton's contribution to the World War II war effort, focused particularly on aviation medicine, can be seen in his correspondence with Hugh Cairns, Hugh DeHaven, and John Lawrence. In addition, the files for Eugene DuBois, Morris Fishbein, Louis Flexner, Lewis Weed, Detlev Bronk, E. Newton Harvey, Charles S. Stephenson, Harold Whittingham, and Solly Zuckerman address both medical subjects and Fulton's work for the National Research Council.
  Files in the series can also be used to trace Fulton's efforts to assist those in need and to support the Allied effort during World War II. He helped European professionals such as David Nachmanson, Edith Meyer and Bruno Kisch when they sought refuge in the United States. He worked with CARE, Inc., American Defense, Harvard Group (which sought universal military training), Medical and Surgical Supply Company, and Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies.
  Fulton's contribution to science included his work as an author and editor. Series I files for the Journal of Neurosurgery and Louise Eisenhardt document the creation of this journal. Though Series II contains the vast majority of correspondence concerning the Journal of Neurophysiology, Series I includes correspondence with fellow editors Ralph Gerard, Lorente de Nó, and Dusser de Barenne. Fulton's publishers also became his friends, as letters from Charles C. Thomas, Henry Schuman, George Banta Company, and W.B. Saunders Company attest. The voluminous correspondence with Charles C. Thomas includes exchanges regarding particular Fulton titles being published and consultations with Fulton about the evaluation of other authors' work.
  Researchers interested in Fulton's correspondence with his family can consult files for his wife, Lucia Pickering Wheatland Fulton, his mother, Edith Fulton, his sisters, Margaret Berg, Laura Booraem, Louise Relf, and Florence Hubbell, and his brother-in-law, Ralph Hubbell. Ralph Hubbell's letters during World War II contain descriptions of his work with the Red Cross in the Soviet Union. Fulton also wrote to his in-laws, Mary and Richard Wheatland, parents of Lucia, and to her brother and sister, David and Martha Wheatland (who married Franc Ingraham). The frequent family letters, both to the Fultons and to the Wheatlands, add details to the already full account recorded in Fulton diaries.
  Letters from unidentified authors are found at the end of the series, as are the annual Christmas letters and the Mill Rock Clarion that Fulton wrote and sent to a large list of correspondents. Both provide useful synopses of events and accomplishments.
  - Ab-Add (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ade-Ald (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ale-Amb (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ame-Amo (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anc-And (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ank-Ar (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - As (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - At-Az (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Abbie, Andrew A., 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Abbott, Kenneth H., 1939-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Abbott, Margaret, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Abbott, Maude, 1928-1939 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Abernethian Society, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Abramson, Harold A., 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Académie Internationale d'Histoire des Sciences, 1937-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ackerknecht, Erwin H., 1945-1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ackerly, Spafford, 1921, 1942, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Acta Physiologica Scandanavia, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Adams, Scott, 1949-1959 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Adams, Theodore, 1933-1953 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Adamson, Joan, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Adelmann, Howard B., 1938-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Adkins, Marguerite, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Adler, Francis H., 1933, 1944-1945, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Adrian, Edgar Douglas, 1923, 1926-1958 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Adson, Alfred W., 1930-1940 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Aero Insurance Underwriters, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Aero Medical Association, 1941-1949, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Aesculapian Club, 1927-1955 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Agerberg, John, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Air Surgeon's Bulletin, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Aitken, Robert S., 1927-1939, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Akçay, Mehmet, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Albers, Bernard J., 1929-1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Alexander, Eben, 1948-1955, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Alexander, Elizabeth H., 1937-1940, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Alexander, Martha, 1949-1957 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - All-India Institute of Medical Sciences, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Allen, Edgar, 1933-1936 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Allen, William F., 1933-1949 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Alpha Omega Alpha, 1927-1956 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Altschul, Frank, 1935-1958 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Alvarez, Walter C., 1931-1956 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Amberson, William, 1924-1926, 1936, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - American Academy for Cerebral Palsy, 1950-1955 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1934-1960 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1924-1959 (Box 4, Folder 50-51)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1931-1953 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - American College of Cardiology, 1956-1959 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1936-1957 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - American Defense, Harvard Group, 1940-1944 (Box 4, Folder 55-56)